Good afternoon, everybody.
Welcome.
It's good to see you.
So today we're going to study an arcane area of computer systems
known as floating point, which is the way that computer systems represent
the real numbers.
So you're all familiar with decimal,
you know, something like 3.14.
And there's a similar idea with binary numbers.
Okay.
So what does a fractional binary number like 1-011.11.
1011 represent?
And how does that work?
Well, it works just like the decimal, fractional decimal numbers that you're used to.
So you have a, in this case, it's a binary point.
And to the left of the binary point, you have bit positions to representing powers of two.
powers of two, so two to the zero, two to the one, two to the two.
So one-half, I'm sorry, one, two, four, and so on.
And to the right of the binary point, you have two to the minus one, one-half,
two to the minus two, one-fourth, two to the minus three, one-eighth, and so on.
And so we can, we can represent any fractional binary number,
using this notation where we sum each the bit at position K times 2 to the k.
Okay, so it's really, it really works exactly the same way as with base 10, just with base 2.
So let's look at some of these, some of these values. So 5 and 3 fourths we would represent as 1.01.1.1.
So this this is before plus one is five plus one half plus one fourth. Okay, so two-fourths plus one-fourth is three-fourth, so five. Okay? So that's, that's pretty simple.
Two and seven-eighths is one-zero point one-one-one-one, so that one-zero is two of course, of course, and then point one-zero is two, of course.
111 is one-half, so four-eighths, plus one-fourth, two-eighths, plus one-eighths, plus one-eighthth.
Okay, so seven-eighths.
And one seven-sixteenths, uh, would be one point zero one-one-one-one-one-one, so that the one to the left of the binary point is one, and then we have one-fourth, plus one-eighth,
1-16th. So one-fourth is 4 sixteenths. One-eighth is two-sixteenths, and one-eighths. So you add those up, you get 7-16th.
Okay, now notice for some of these numbers, we, this bit pattern, one-zero-1.11, if we, if we shift it to the right to get 1-1-1-1-1, if we shift it to the right to get 1-1-1,
we've divided by two, right?
So we've taken five and three-fourths and divided it by two.
And it works the other way, too.
If you shift to the left, you multiply.
If you shift to the left by one, you multiply.
And these numbers that are all ones to the right of the binary point are,
these are numbers that are just slightly less than one.
Okay.
And so we'll, well, we'll, we want to represent.
those will often, we'll sometimes refer to those numbers of that form as 1 minus
epsilon.
And epsilon just depends on how many bits you have to the right of the binary point.
So epsilon gets smaller, the more of those bits you have.
Or it gets closer to 1.
And epsilon gets smaller the more of those bits you have.
Now there's limitations in this kind of representation.
representation. So, first of all, we can only represent rational numbers of the form x divided by 2 to the k.
We can only represent numbers of that form exactly. Other numbers have to get, have repeating bit representations that can't be represented with the finite number of bits that we have in a computer system.
So, for example, things like one-third is this repeating representation, one-fifth and one-tenth.
other examples of that.
Now the other problem we have is that we can only, there's only so many bits to the left and
the right of the binary point. So we're kind of, if we put, if we move the binary point to
the left, then we don't have as many, we can't represent as many large numbers. We can
only represent small numbers, but we have more precision to the right of the binary point.
So we can represent more fractional values.
Just the range of those values will be much smaller.
Similarly, if we move the binary point to the right, we'll have a larger range of values, but we won't be able to represent as many fractions.
Okay.
So there's this, there's this kind of trade-off, and floating point is a representation to try, that enables us to move that, that enables us to move that, basically,
that binary point to represent sort of as wide a range as possible with as much
precision given the number of bits, the finite number of bits that we have to work with.
So the float and the floating point is this sort of shifting binary point, right?
This floating, this floating binary point.
Now up until 1985, floating point was just a disaster. And every computer manufacturer had
their own representation. You couldn't, and it was just terrible, because you couldn't
predict what would happen if you moved your program from one machine to another. The behavior
would be different, the rounding would be different. It was a very difficult situation.
And people really, computer scientists in particular, really disliked floating
point.
In 1885, I-3-E, which is the professional association for electrical engineers, introduced a, and it's
also a very important standards body, they introduced a standard floating-point representation
called I-Triple-E floating-point, which was then adopted by all computer manufacturers.
So now the situation is much better.
everybody supports the same kind of floating point representation,
which is what we're going to learn about today.
So the floating point has the form, it represents numbers in a, this is like a
scientific notation, it represents numbers of the form minus 1 to the S, where
is a sign bit times a significant m times 2 to some exponent e.
Okay, so all of the numbers that we can represent in floating point have to be represented
in this form. So the sign bit s determines whether the number is negative or positive, obviously,
the significant M, and this is some sort of the sign bit s determines whether the number is negative or positive,
sometimes call them Antissa, which is where the M comes from.
The significant M normally is a fractional value in the range between between 1 and 2.
And we'll see, we'll see why that is in a second.
And then the exponent E weights the value by some power of 2.
Okay, so this is encoded in either 32 bits or 64 bits in the following way.
The sine bit S is the most significant bit, and then this is followed by
some number of by some number of bits called the EXP field, which encodes the
the exponent E, but it's not identical to E. It encodes E. It encodes E. And we'll see how that works.
And then the frac, and then that's followed. The remaining bits are the frack field, which encodes
M but isn't identical to M. Now we, I-Triplea floating point.
The floating point provides two different kinds of floating point.
There's single precision, 32 bits, and so-called double precision, which is 64 bits.
There's this funky Intel extended precision, which is non-standard, and we won't talk about it anymore.
And so in the single precision, 32 bits, you have one signed bit, there's always a sign bit.
You have eight EXP bits and you have 23 frack bits. In double precision, you have
11 EXP bits and 52 frac bits.
Now, there's a number of different kinds of floating point representations.
The sort of the default and sort of the common representation is called normalized, so-called
normalized values. And normalized values are all the values where the EXP field is not equal to zero and
not equal to all zeros and not equal to all ones.
Okay, so everything, all zeros and all ones are special kinds of numbers we'll look at in a second.
So the exponent, this exponent E, remember our numbers are minus 1 to the power S times
m times 2 raise to the power E. The exponent E is encoded as this biased to the power E. The exponent E is
encoded as this biased value, which is the called EXP.
So the X, the exponent E is E is EXP minus some bias.
And EXP is the value, capital EXP is the value of the
XP bits, the bits in the EXP field, treated as a positive number.
Okay, so capital EXP is just, you just look at it as an unsigned,
7-bit, in case of single precision, 7-bit number.
Okay.
Now the bias is 2 to the power k minus 1, minus 1,
where k is the number of exponent bits.
Okay, so for single precision, we have 8 exponent bits.
So 2 to the 8th, 2 to the 8 minus 1 is 7.
So 2 to the 7th is 2 to the 7th is 1,
minus 1 is 127. Okay, so the bias for single precision is 127. And similarly, similarly, for double precision, it's 123.23.
Okay, so you just, you just have to memorize this, this formula. The exponent E is the EXP field interpreted as an unsigned number minus the bias.
Now this is a, this is kind of a strange thing.
the first time you encounter floating point, it seems kind of odd, right?
So why not, I mean, we've already learned about two's complement.
That's a perfectly fine way to represent positive and negative numbers.
And we have exponents that are negative and positive, right?
So why not just use the EXP field to represent, or why not just use two's complement in the EXP field
to represent those positive and negative exponents, right?
So it turns to use two's complement in the EXP field to represent those positive.
out that the reason that they do this is that, and if you think about, think about
this and we'll come back to it, but if we, if we encode the the exponent E using this bias representation,
the smallest negative exponent is represented by all zeros, okay, and the largest exponent is represented
by all zeros.
And the largest exponent is represented by 0-1-1-1-1-1.
So the smallest, the number with the smallest exponent, if we were just to compare the bits using
just some kind of unsigned representation, just comparing the bits, treating it as an unsigned
number, by using this biased representation, we can just compare two floating-point
numbers just as unsigned we can treat the whole floating point number
as an unsigned integer and compare two numbers and get get a true comparison so the
exponent uses this this sort of biasing encoding and then the significant is
encoded with an implied one so and this is where the this is where the normalized in the
the normalized representation comes from that we're always
going to represent our numbers.
So M, we're always going to normalize M, no matter what the number we want to represent, we're always
going to normalize M as one point something.
And then we adjust the exponent accordingly.
All right, so if if the value we want to represent is 100.01, we're going to shift it over,
and it'll be 1.00.00, okay.
And then we'll adjust the exponent.
to represent that shift.
Okay, so the bits in the frack field,
XXXXXXXX, X are all of the numbers to the right of the binary point, right?
So there's always this implied one.
But we don't even encode it.
We just throw it away because it's always there.
So this is a little trick just to get one more bit for free.
Okay, so the xXX bits in the frack field
are all the bits to the right of the binary point after one point, the one point.
And this is the, so this is the smallest frack field is all zeros, which corresponds to a significant of 1.0.
Okay.
And a frack field of all ones corresponds to 2 minus epsilon.
So that's 1.1111, so on.
So let's look at.
Let's look at an example. So let's look at how we would encode 15213, which our favorite number,
in 2's in floating point. So the, if we represent that, so it's an integer, and we represent it using
using these bits, take my word for it, correspond to the integer 213. So now we want to convert it,
we want to normalize it, we want to normalize it, by expressing it as the integer 213.
by expressing it as 1.110 and so on times 2 to the 13th.
Okay, same number we just normalized it so that there's there's always this leading one.
So the significant M is 1.11011 and so on.
The frack field is everything to the right of the binary point. So we just, we throw this, we throw this one away, and we just take the
the values to the right of the binary point, and then we pad it out with zeros
to get the 23 bits that we need for single precision.
Okay, so now we've got our frack field.
The exponent, so in this case,
right, E is, we're multiplying by 2 to the 13th, so E is 13.
So we want to represent the value 13 using this biased encoding.
So the bias is 127, and so the bias is 127, and so the
exponent, the value of the EXP field, should be 140.
Because if we take, if we take 140 minus 127, we get 13.
Okay, so 140 is represented using these 8 bits, and that becomes our EXP field.
Okay, so the resulting floating point number, and of course, it's a positive number, so the sine bit is 0.
So the resulting floating point number has these 8, the 8 bits in the EXP field that we computed by subtracting 140, by subtracting 127 from 140.
And then the frack field are these bits that we got here by just taking everything to the right of the binary point.
So this, so let's look at this exponent just a little bit more, because I think, can be a little bit more.
It can be a little confusing.
So in our example, if we want to look at the range of EXP, so what's the smallest value of EXP?
What's the smallest value of EXP?
No, wait a minute, don't confuse the encoding with the value it represents.
EXP is just the encoding.
So what's the smallest value of EXP?
Zero, that's right.
Okay.
And the largest value is.
is what?
What's the largest value?
Yes.
Well, the largest value would be, remember, it can't be all ones.
Right?
So the largest value would be 2 to the 8th minus 1.
So.
Okay, so the largest value would be 0, 1-1-1-1, 0 followed by 7-1s.
Okay.
So that's 2 to the 8th minus 1 is 250.
255, good.
Okay, so then what's the range then of the of E,
which is the actual value that we want to encode?
Okay, remember, use this, we have this definition.
So we have the range of values for EXP.
We have our bias.
So what is the range of values for E?
This is the actual exponents that we're encoding.
So what's the smallest exponent?
Minus 127, good.
Right?
Because that's 0.
0.
is our smallest EXP minus the bias, which is 127.
Okay?
So the smallest value of E is, is, is, is, is,
and the largest value of E is, so if we take the largest value of EXP, that's 255, minus 127, 128.
Okay, so the numbers that we can represent, using this biased notation, we'll have the smallest
will be 2 to the minus 127, and the largest exponent will be 2 to the raise of the power 128.
Okay, so do you see, do you see what's going on here?
So we have a range of values for E.
Here's the largest value, here's the smallest value,
and here's zero right in the middle.
These are the values we want to represent.
This biasing is like a shift.
We've just, now we're shifting up by 127,
so that now the smallest exponent,
exponent is represented by 0.
Any questions about that?
Now, these normalized values always have this implied
values always have this implied 1, okay, which when we get close, when we want to
represent numbers closer to zero, that limits us, right?
So there's another type of floating point number called a denorm, denormalized value,
which which is characterized by a
EXP field of all zeros.
And in a denormalized number, or denorm,
there's no implied one.
Okay, so the significant M is represented exactly,
is encoded identically in the frac field.
So there's no implied one, and all of the numbers are the
form 0 point something, something, something after them.
And the exponent value E,
Instead of, you remember, for D norms,
we subtracted bias from EXP.
For D norms, we subtract the bias from 1.
Okay.
Now, you would, if we just use the definition we use for normalized numbers,
that would be, the EXP would be 0, so we don't do that.
Instead, we, we, we, uh,
E is 1 minus the bias.
And then the significant is coded with an implied leading 0
instead of a leading 1, like I mentioned.
So when EXP is zero, and also, I mean, we think about it, if we only had denormalized numbers, we wouldn't be able to represent zero, right?
Because there'd always be a one in there.
So the denorms allow us to represent zero, and they allow us to represent values that are very close to zero.
So when the exponent is zero, and the EXP field is zero, and the frack field is zero, then this is the zero
And so this is nice because all zeros represents zero, which is, you know, sort of what what you want.
Now there is this sort of weird thing, though, that if you have a, the sign bit is one, and then
your frack and EXP are zero, then you have negative zero. So you have this kind of odd situation where there's a positive and negative zero.
Okay. And other values, if EXP is zero and you have a non-0, and you have a non-zero,
zero frac, then those are the equally spaced numbers that are closest to zero.
Now there's a couple of other special values. When EXP is all ones and the frack is all zeros, this
represents the value infinity. So this is a value that we get when we do some kind of addition
or multiplication and we overflow. So in floating point always overflows to this special value
called infinity, either positive or negative.
of infinity. So it's different from two's complement, right, where you sort of overflowed
into in this modular way back, just back around into the range of numbers. And in floating point,
we just overflow to the sticky value called infinity, and then then everything we do on that remains
infinity. So for example, if we did a, if we did a, if we did one divided by zero, or we did minus one divided by
minus 0, we'd get positive infinity. If we divide 1 by a 0, negative 0, we get negative
infinity. The fourth, the fourth kind of special case, special number, is the case where the
exponent again is all ones, but the frac is non-zero, any non-zero value. And this represents
what's called not a number. So this is, this is, this, this handles cases where there's no answer.
There's no feasible answer. For example, if we, you know, try to take the square root of minus 1, what we'll get back is not a number.
So to, I think it's helpful to, to visualize these, the number line now. So the, the, we have positive 0, negative 0, sort of right next to each other. And then to the right of that are the positive D norms, and then those, then those sort of transition into the,
the normalized numbers, and then you have infinity, positive infinity.
You have a similar, similar situation on the, for the negative numbers, and then negative and
positive, not a numbers.
So I think the, you know, you've probably, you've probably discovered now that the bit, a really good way to
try to understand these numerical coding is just to do examples with only a few number of bits.
You know, if you want to understand, like, for example, in two's
complement. If you want to understand T-min and T-max and how they relate to each other,
just do a three-bit two's complement system. You know, imagine just have a system with two's complement
three-bits. And then you can just enumerate all those, all the possibilities, and you can see, and then
you see where, you know, the T-min is actually one greater than T-max, you know, so if you
add one to T-max, it actually overflows into T-min.
Similar thing for floating point, it's, I would really encourage you to do this, just try some simple examples with a sort of tiny, with a small number of EXP and frack bits.
So in this case, we're, we're going to look at a floating point system based on I-Triple-E that has four EXP bits and three frack bits.
As always, the sign bit is the most significant bit, followed by XP, followed by frack.
Okay. So this is identical to I-Triple-E floating point except for the size of the
EXP and fract fields. So it's actually small enough that we can now just enumerate these values. And
and now you can, you can start to see why these weird definitions for the exponent in denorms and normalized numbers.
So let's just look at, so what we've done here,
we've just, with a signed bit of zero, we've just enumerated all of the two to the seven possibilities, possible combinations of EXP and frack fields, starting with zero.
Okay, so when EXP is all zeros, that's a D norm, right, by definition. And then we have the three frack bits are all zero. Okay, so remember the EXP is all zeros, right?
So for denorms, the, the, the, the, uh, the exponent value is one minus the bias.
Our bias here is seven. Okay, so one minus seven, okay? So one minus seven gives us a value for the
exponent of minus six. So we're going to take the frack, um, the bits in the, in the frack field, um, times. So m is zero. So m in this case is zero, times two to
the minus sixth gives us zero. So this, this is our representation of zero. And like
I said, it's really, it's nice that it actually is, if we just treated this as an unsigned integer,
it would just, it would be zero. Okay, so that's kind of pleasing. Now let's look at the very next number,
right? The X, EXP is still zero, and we've just bumped up frac by one. Okay, so again, it's, it's
So one minus the bias, which is minus six.
And now this frac field represents, this is one-half, one-fourth, one-eighth.
So it represents, so this is a value of m is, is one-eighth, so one-eighth times two to the minus
six, which is one-sixty-fourth, equals one over five-twilth.
So in this floating point system, the smallest non-zero number we can represent,
is the denormalized representation of 1 over 512.
The next smallest number is 0.
Okay, now let's look at, so let's take, let's bump this up by 1, so now we get a, we get a frac
field of 0, 1,0.
So this represents 1 4th, so EM is 1 4th, the significant is 1 4th, times 2 to the minus 6th.
So 2 eighths times 164th is 2.
the 512s.
Okay, so the numbers, we're just, by incrementing this,
by incrementing our significant, we're increasing the numbers by 1 over 512.
Now the largest denorm in this number system is the case where the frack field is all ones.
And so this encodes 1⁄2th plus 1⁄2th, plus 1⁄2th, and so this encodes 1⁄.
which is 7 eighths.
And then our value is 7 eighths times 2 to the minus 6,
or 1 over 64, that equals 7.512s.
So this 7 over 512s is the largest denormalized number we can represent in this system.
And now if we bump our number up by 1,
the frack field resets to 0, and now the EXP field goes from 0 to 1.
to 1. Now, because the EXP field is non-0, this is no longer a denormalized number, it's a normalized number.
Okay, so now we're changing the definition of E from 1 minus the bias to EXP minus the bias.
So what's EXP in this case? 1. Minus 7, the bias, is minus 6. So lo and behold, it's the
It's the same exponent as the previous denormalized number.
So this is actually very clever by the ICCA folks because you get this very, you get this nice,
smooth transition from denorms to norm to normalized.
So you can see that our exponent E is minus 6 still, and now our because we're taking 1 minus the
bias 7 and our significant, now remember this is a normalized number
because the EXP field is non-zero.
This, this, the frack field of all zeros, represents a significant of 1.0000.
Okay, so this normalized number, this is the smallest normalized number, represents is 1.00,
which is 8 eighths, times 2.
2 to the minus 6, which is 1 over 64, which gives us 8 over 512.
So we've made this nice smooth transition from 7 over 512 to 8 over 512.
And I'll do one more.
I don't want to, so if we bump, if we bump keeping the EXP field at 1, if we bump our frack field from 0 to 1,
now this represents the the, the, the, uh, significant of 1.01, which is 8ths plus 1 eighth, so that's, so that's 9 eighths, times, times, and then the 8ths plus 1 eighths, so that's 9 eighths, and then the
is 9.8ths times 2 to the minus 6, once 1 over 64, which is equal to 9 over 512.
Okay? Any questions about that? Question back here? Okay, the question is why is, why do you choose
the bias that to be 2 to the k minus 1 minus 1 minus 1? Well, go back to my, my finger diagram here. So this is the range of
of Exp fields that you want to, this is the range of E that you want to represent with 0 in the middle. Okay.
And so you want to bias it so that this is halfway.
Zero, the smallest exponent is halfway to zero.
So you want the bias to shift it up, so it's the smallest,
the smallest encoded, the smallest value of EXP corresponds to the smallest
exponent. Right, so 2 to the k minus 1 minus 1 is just giving you,
it's giving you a value that's halfway between the smallest
exponent and the largest exponent. Okay, that's good. Any other questions?
Okay, if we take a, like a, a, uh,
a little smaller six-bit format, same thing as we did before, just different numbers of bits in EXP and FRAC.
And then we plot these on the number line. You can see that, you can see that the values are very dense
around zero, so they're very spaced very closely together. And then every time you increase
the exponent by one, the numbers are spaced twice as far apart as the exponent by one, the numbers are spaced by one, the numbers
are spaced twice as twice as far apart as the previous the numbers that were represented by the previous exponent.
So you can see, like in this little example, you see these values here are all equally spaced.
Now these four values are equally spaced and they're right next to each other.
And then you see this jump in the spacing, that represents an increase in the spacing, that represents an increase
in the EXP field by one and then it and then that spacing doubles as we go out.
And you can see it, you can see it even better here. This, if we, if we zoom in, these blue values are
the, these blue values are denorms, and then we have the next set of normalized values where the
frack field is one. They're spaced the same, right? We saw this when we kept increasing by
by 1 over 512.
And then we increase the exponent by 1 and the spacing doubles.
Okay, so this, like I mentioned, this encoding has some pretty nice properties.
The floating point zero is encoded as integer 0, which is nice.
And with the exception of not a number, with the exception of not a number, you can compare, you can compare
any floating point numbers, including infinity, by just treating it as doing
an unsigned comparison. So that's really nice, too. Now, if you, when you add and multiply floating
point numbers, right, we're dealing with a limited set of bits here. So if we take two
numbers encoded as floating point and we add them together, there's, there's no
guarantee that we'll be able to fit all those bits in the bits we have available to us.
There's no guarantee that we'll be able to fit the bits in the result.
So what we do in this case is you can imagine the model you want to have of floating point operations, addition and multiplication,
is that you add or multiply, you do the addition or multiplication, and you compute the exact result.
You just assume that you have an infinite amount or number of bits.
And then you round use the technique called rounder,
to get it to fit into the available bits.
Okay. So the effect is, like I'm doing, say, x plus y, is getting the precise value of x plus y is getting
the precise value of x plus y in an infinite number of bits and then rounding into the available bits.
So let's look at this idea of rounding.
It, this can be confusing the first time you see it. It requires, it requires, you need to
think about it carefully to get it right.
Now in I-Triple-E, there's four different kinds of rounding.
There's round towards zero, round down, round to minus infinity, round up to, which is
rounding it to positive infinity, and then the default case, which is the only one
we're really going to consider, which is round to the nearest even.
And this is what I-Tri-EE does by default.
You can, you can, if you go into a
assembly language, you can change that rounding, but we're not going to consider it anymore.
Yes, question.
I'm sorry?
Is there a distinct negative infinity apart from the...
There is, right, because there's one...
So the question is there a distinct negative infinity and a distinct positive infinity.
And there is. They have the exact same bit representation except the most significant bit for negative infinity
is one, and for positive infinity it's zero.
Yes, question.
Why does it?
Right is nearest even?
Round to one.
Oh, I'll show you.
Let me go over the other.
The question was about nearest even.
Yes.
Doesn't that make negative infinity greater than the positive?
Well, that was the exception, right?
That's right.
So aside from infinity, you can't do that comparison.
How about?
Positive infinity works, right?
But not negative.
So you're right.
Good point.
All right, so let's look at these rounding modes, and I'll explain why the nearest even works.
But, let's look at, so rounding towards zero, what we're going to do, we'll use dollars.
So we want to round to the nearest dollar.
Towards zero, just anything less than, you just round, you just round towards zero.
So a dollar 40 would go to one, a dollar 60 would go down to one, a dollar 50 to 1, 250 would go to 2.
Negative 150, you round towards zero, so that would be negative, negative 1.
Round down towards negative infinity.
It's similar. The only difference is that for negative $1.
Negative $1.50, you'd round towards negative infinity, which would be minus 2.
Rounding up is the, is the, is symmetric to round down.
The interesting case is round to nearest even.
Interesting because it's what IAA floating point actually uses.
So the idea here,
If you have a value that's less than half, then you round down.
If you have a value that's more than halfway between two dollar amounts, you round up.
The round, the nearest even part comes,
when you have something that's exactly halfway, then what you do is you round towards the nearest even number.
Okay.
So in, in this example, a dollar 40, because it's less than, it's less than half way,
it's less than half, rounds down to $1.
A $1.60 is greater than half, so we round up to $2.
$1.50, right in the middle.
We round up to the nearest even dollar amount, which is $2.
$2.50 cents, we round down to the nearest even, right?
If we round it up, it would be three, which is an odd number.
And minus $1.50, we round to $1.
we round down to minus $2.
So the reason we do this, the reason they chose this is that statistically,
if you would imagine, if you have a uniform distribution of sort of numbers,
they're going to round up or down about 50% of the time,
so there won't be a statistical bias rounding up or down one way or the other.
Okay, so that's the, that's the reason they did that.
Now, you can apply this, you can do this
rounding to any value.
So in the last example, we did it to the nearest dollar.
But suppose we wanted to round to the nearest hundredth,
using round to even, the default round to even mode.
So we want to round to round to the nearest hundredth
is this second position.
This first, do we have tenths, then hundreds.
So if we have a value 7.89-49-999, 499999,
That's less than halfway, right?
Halfway would be, halfway would be any number that had a five followed by all zeros.
So 499 is less than that.
So we would just round down to 7.89, even though 9 is odd.
The only, the only time we're going to apply round to even is when we're exactly halfway.
Okay, our next, the next example, 7.89501, that's greater than half way.
If this was a zero, it would be exactly halfway.
So we round up to 7.9.9.
Okay, now here's the interesting case where we have 7.895 followed by all zeros.
That's exactly halfway.
So now we apply the round to nearest even rule.
Eight, nine is a negative, is an odd number, so that doesn't work.
So we round up, and we do that basically by adding a five,
adding a 5 here, so 5 and 5 is 10, and then that carries over to the next position,
and 9 and 1 is 0, 9 and 1 is 10, so that carries over, and 8 plus 1 is 9.
So the result of rounding up is 7.90.
Okay, is that clear?
Do you see?
It's a very mechanical way.
When you round up, it's always, it's a very mechanical like that.
You always just add.
the halfway number, in this case five, and then just propagate it out, just do the addition,
and that'll give you the nearest, the nearest, that'll round you up to the nearest hundredth in this case.
Okay, now the last case, 7.885 followed by all zeros, that's another number that's halfway between
two numbers rounded to the nearest hundredth. So in this case,
8 is even, so we just, we round down, and to round down, we just truncate.
Just throw these bits, these, these digits away, and we get 7.888.
So there are any questions about this?
Question back here. Yes.
But, so is it through that?
Yes, that's, so the question was if numbers that have the same EXP field, will the, will those numbers be equally spaced on the number line?
And the answer is yes.
Yes, question.
Rounding up or down, we consider all the, like, the entire value to the right of the place your rounding.
Like, if in the last example, there was one at the end, it would round up.
It would round up.
Yeah, the only, the halfway values are always, in this case, because it's base 10.
The halfway number in base 10 is 5.
And then, so it's always the halfway number, in this case 5, followed by all zeros.
you'll always have that the halfway, if a value is halfway between like 200s, it'll always have that form.
All right.
Now we can do the same thing with binary fractional numbers as well.
Now, a binary number is even if the least significant digit is zero.
Okay, we only have two digits, right? So odd is one and zero.
Okay.
And the halfway, so the halfway value is going to be a one followed by all zeros.
Okay, that represents exactly halfway.
So it's very, it's analogous, analogous to the base 10 example, except where the halfway value is going to be one followed by all zeros.
So let's look, let's look at some examples.
So suppose we have, we want to represent two and three, three, three,
And suppose we only have four bits to do that in.
Okay, well, to represent that exactly, we need seven bits, and so we have to round.
Okay.
So let's look at, so we're going to round to this two bits right of the binary point.
And so let's look at all the bits that follow that.
So since it starts with zero, this is going to be less than halfway.
So since it's less than halfway, we just truncate, just chop those out, and the result is
one 0.00.
Now our next example is one zero point zero one one zero.
So if we look at these, the bits to the right of the, to the right of the, the bit we're rounding to,
um, since it starts with one and it's not followed by all zeros, that's greater than half.
than half. So, for the, in this case, we have to round up. And so the way we do that
is we take, we take one and we add it to this leftmost one right here and just do the addition,
and the result is one 0.01. Now let's look at 2 to the 7 eighths. This is represented as
one 0.111.00. Now here's that, here's that halfway,
marker that we were looking for. It's a 1 followed by all 0. So this is exactly
halfway. So now we have to round to the nearest even number. Now, the, if we can't just truncate
because then that would be an odd number, right? We would end 1.1.1 is an odd number. So we have
to round up, and we do that by adding, we do that by adding a 1 right here to this, to this
left most red bit, we add one to that, and then just do the addition, and we end up with
with 1.0.00, which is 3. So the nearest, the nearest value to 2 to the 7th, the nearest
rounded value is 3. Okay, our last example, 2 to the 5 a's, we have the same halfway marker again, 1,0,0. But in this
case, the hundredth bit, or the one-fourth bit, is zero, so that's even. So we can
just truncate. We just throw those bits away, and the result is simply 1-0.10.10.
That makes sense? So it's very mechanical. Mainly, you just need to be able to recognize that halfway
marker, and then figure out if you need to round up or down. If you're going to round
down, just truncate. If you're going to round up, add a one and just propagate it to get
your result.
Okay.
We won't spend much time.
I just want to mention a few things about multiplication and addition.
So if we multiply two numbers, so we have different mantises, significance, and exponents, and
exponents.
And suppose that the result is m times 2 to the e, the sine bit will be the x-or of the two
bits of the two operands.
The sign bit will be the x-or of the two sine bits of the two operands.
The significant M will be multiplying m1 times m2, and the exponents are added, right?
Because they're just by the rules of exponents.
So if M is greater than 2, and this is a normalized number, we have to, we have to shift it.
We have to put it in the range between 1 and 2 by shifting to the right and incrementing
the exponent.
If e is out of range, then we overflow to infinity.
And then if M has too many bits, we have to use round to even to fit it into the available
frac bits.
Okay.
Addition, so suppose we're trying to add to floating point numbers.
Conceptually what you do is think of those numbers as fractional binary numbers.
You want to line up the binary points, line up the binary points, then do the addition, and then do the addition,
and then do the addition.
And then normalize the number
so that the normalize the significance so that it's between one and two.
And either do that by shifting shifting right or left.
If E is too big, then you overflow, and then you round the bits in M to fit into the available frack field.
Now, you remember when we, the first day of class, we talked about what you call these great realities,
that ints aren't really integers and floats aren't really reals.
So the, and just as, just as we saw when we looked at two's complement representation of integers,
it's not exactly, they're not exactly like real integers, and operations on them aren't exactly like real integers,
but they follow very predictable mathematical properties, okay, that are similar to integers, but not quite.
So the same thing holds for floating point numbers.
point numbers. They follow very predictable, they have very predictable
they have very predictable mathematical mathematics, but they're somewhat different from the reals. And the
And the big, the big thing with addition is that it doesn't associate. Okay,
it's commutative, but it's not associative. And this usually happens when you have, when you have,
have when you're dealing with numbers that have very large dynamic ranges.
So a big, if you're trying to add and subtract really big numbers with really little numbers,
you run into this problem of non-associativity.
So the example was if we take 3.14 plus 2 to the 10th, 2 to the 10th is so, is so much larger
than 3.14, that would be 2 to the 10th plus 3.14, the bits that represent
the 3.14, you know, there's bits way out here that represent, there's one bit out here that represents
2 to the 10th, and then there's a few bits here that represent 3.14. And there's just not enough,
we don't have enough bits to represent all those. So we have, the 3.14 goes, goes away. So adding a big number
to a little number essentially gives the big number, and then if you subtract
that big number, you get zero. Now, if we change the association, if we take this big number and
subtract it from itself, we get zero, and then, so the result will be instead of zero as before
we get 3.14. So other than that, you have all of the things that you have all of the things that you would
normally expect. Closed under addition, it's community.
there's an additive identity of zero. Except for infinities and nans, there's
there's an additive inverse. You can take for any number, there's there's an inverse that'll
give you zero when you add it together. And you get monoticity, monotonicity between
values, except of course, for infinities and nans. Now multiplication has, it's similar. It's similar. You get
it's closed generally under multiplication, it's commutative, but it's not associative,
and it doesn't distribute over addition. And it's the same. So here you can see we're
taking 2 to the 20th times 2 to the 20th times 2 to the 20th, and so that gives infinity. But
if we, if we reassociate and we take, I'm sorry, two to the 20 times 2 to the 20th times 2 to the minus
20th. Well, this first multiplication is infinity, and anything you do with infinity
is just infinity. So the result is infinity. However, if we reassociate and multiply 2 to the 20th
times 2 to the minus 20th, that gives us 1, and then multiplied by 2 to the 20th, and so we get 2 to
the 20th. So the big takeaway point here is that a floating point, floating point isn't
Now, is that a problem? It's something you have to be aware of.
And, but generally, I mean, I've done a lot of scientific computing in particular modeling,
earthquake ground motion in Southern California. So basically, we would build models of Southern California
in the computer, and then we would shake them, and then we would see how the ground moves in, like,
and then we would see how the ground moves in, like, like, and those, that shaking, that shaking,
That shaking, we used a numerical method called finite elements, and it was all,
it used all floating point, single precision floating point numbers.
And we never ran into a problem with this associativity, right?
We would do, we would do operations in different orders.
We couldn't always guarantee that we would do the operations in the exact same order.
But we never ran into a problem with this because nature in general, in general, is
kind of smooth, right?
That if you look at the, you know, if one part of the ground is shaking,
like this and you look at the next part, it might be shaking a little more or a little less,
but you're not going to have huge differences. And so we never ran into those kind of problems.
But in some, so if you, generally, if you're, if you're simulating natural phenomena, you don't
often see these kind of huge dynamic ranges. But other times, you know, if it's not
non-natural, financial, maybe financial systems, they use floating point, then you might
see these larger dynamic ranges of numbers and it might become a problem.
So as a programmer, you just generally have to be aware of this. You have to have to have a good sense
for the dynamic range of your numbers. And you have to keep in mind that if you, if you
reassociate or change the order of things, you may not get exactly the same, exactly the same
answer. Okay. Now, C gives us two different kinds of floating points. So they, the float
is the IEEE single precision and double is the IE double precision.
Now, you remember when we did casting between ints and unsigned values back and forth, the cast
never changed the bit representation. It just changed the way that, in fact, it never even changed
the, the, the, the, how the ALU manipulated those bits. It's really just a, how we're
interpreting and how we're viewing those values.
However, when you do cast between floats and ints and doubles, the bit representation
changes.
Right? So a cast here has a dramatic effect on the actual bits themselves.
Now, if we go from a double or a float to an int, it's going to, it's just going to, it's going to truncate
the fractional part and give us the, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, give us the, uh, uh,
uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, and then, and then,
round to fit. Oh, actually, no, there won't be, okay, so think about this.
How many there were, we said 23, 23 frac bits in float, and I forget exactly how many
in doubles.
You can't remember, it doesn't matter.
It's some, it's some number, well, no, it does matter, let's, so for a float, if we, if we
cast a float to an int, we're casting 23, something that we can represent with
23, at most 23, frac bits, uh, into a 32-bit in.
So we won't, we'll never lose, so we won't, we'll never need to do any rounding.
Um, but double precision has 52 bits. Okay, so there, there we may not be able to fit the, the,
the represented integer into the, uh, into the int, so they'll, um, they'll have to be some rounding. Sorry,
PowerPoint crashed. Okay. Right now, if we cast, if we cast from an int to a double,
there, we'll have, we'll have enough bits, so we won't lose anything, right? The 32 bits will fit
in the double precision frack field. And, but int to float has, there's more, there's more bits in
an int than there are in the frack field of a float, so we'll have to do some rounding, right?
So the, so casting works the same way as any other operating.
You can think of it as just taking the, assume you have an infinite number of bits, get the exact result, and then round it to fit into the available bits.
All right, so let's, the final thing I want to do today is sort of test your understanding, do you solve some puzzles to test, test our understanding of these properties of floating point numbers.
So imagine that we have three values, x is an int, f is a float, and d is a double.
double and then we're we're evaluating the c the c expressions so
x is x equal to int float x yeah oh you can edit out the you can edit out the you
can edit out that other stuff all right so what do you think if we so if we take x which is an
an int cast it to a float and then cast that back to an int will that always be equal to x
no no right because we lose some bits right we don't
have enough frack bits in float.
What about if we take x, cast it to a double,
and then cast it back to end?
Will we always get equivalent value?
Yeah, because we have enough frack bits in double.
Now what if we take a float F, cast it to a double,
and then cast it back to a float?
Will that always equal the original F?
Yeah.
What about the converse though?
What if we take the double D, cast it to a
float and cast it back to a double?
No?
How about this?
How about if we take F, negate it, and then negate that again, will that always equal F?
Yeah, because we're just toggling a bit, right?
So, okay, how about 2 over 3 equal 2 over 3.0?
No, because 2 over 3 is 0, and 2 over 3.0 is a floating point value, two-thirds,
thirds, the floating point representation of 2 thirds.
Okay, how about if the double D is less than?
zero does that imply that D times 2 is also less than 0?
Yeah.
Even if, no matter what, even if 2 times D overflows, it'll overflow to negative infinity, which is less
than, which is less than 0.
Okay, how about does the double D greater than F imply that minus F is greater than
minus D?
Yeah, that's that monotonicity, right?
And again, it's just, yes.
It's just, yes.
Is that a float or a double?
Oh, that's a good question.
I think it would be a float.
I think if you put, there's an annotation in C to give it a double.
But actually, I'd have to check that out.
That's an F, yeah.
That's a good question.
I don't know.
We'd have to check.
I'll have to go and look in the C guide.
How about if is D squared, the double D squared,
always greater than are equal to zero?
Yes.
And how about does D plus F minus D always equal F?
No, because of lack of associativity.
Okay.
So that was fun, right? Floating point's always fun.
So anyway, the big thing is just to realize that floats aren't exactly really reals,
but they have very predictable properties,
and that they're not associative or commutative.
They're not associative.
So you have to be careful.
about that.
All right, we'll have a good weekend and we'll see you on Tuesday.